Guide to the Joel Garreau Papers, 1954-1994
George Mason University Libraries
- Series 1: Edge City, 1959-February 1994
  - Subseries 1.11: Miscellaneous, July 1987-June 1992
    - California Community, November 1988 (Box 51, Folder 29)
      Articles and notes about community and California.
    - California, June 1992 (Box 51, Folder 30)
      Notes and an article about California divisions.
    - San Francisco, May-June 1992 (Box 51, Folder 31)
      Articles about different sections of California.
    - Notes, January 1990 (Box 51, Folder 32)
      Notes about various subjects.
    - Venice Mike Kernan, October-December 1988 (Box 51, Folder 33)
      An article about Venice, Italy and notes about Mike Kernan. Theory
    - Central Europe, June 1990 (Box 51, Folder 34)
      An article about changes in Central Europe.
    - Individualism, November 1989 (Box 51, Folder 35)
      An article about practices in Asia worth copying in America.
    - Chador, February 1989 (Box 51, Folder 36)
      An article about Iranian traditional dress codes for women.
    - Core Values, April 1990 (Box 51, Folder 37)
      Articles about the change in ideologies over growth.
    - Choice, April 1989 (Box 51, Folder 38)
      An article about choices available to consumers.
    - John Winthrop, Undated (Box 51, Folder 39)
      An article about John Winthrop and Christian principles. Also included are excerpts from John Milton poems.
    - Homeless, June 1989 (Box 51, Folder 40)
      An article about homelessness in Manhattan.
    - Spirituality, July 1987-June 1989 (Box 51, Folder 41)
      Articles about religion in politics and daily life.
    - Time, April 1989-January 1990 (Box 51, Folder 42)
      Articles about time management.
    - U.S.-U.S.S.R., October 1989 (Box 52, Folder 1)
      An article about American-Soviet relations.
    - Dematerializing, May 1989 (Box 52, Folder 2)
      An article about still video cameras.
    - Disneyland, June 1990 (Box 52, Folder 3)
      Articles, brochures, and guides to Disneyland
    - Knott's Berry Farm, May 1990 (Box 52, Folder 4)
      An article about Knott's Berry Farm
    - William Goldschmidt, June 1990 (Box 52, Folder 5)
      An article about UCLA professor William Goldschmidt.
    - South Coast Community Church, May-July 1990 (Box 52, Folder 6)
      Publications from South Coast Community Church.
    - The Christian Business and Professional Directory, 1989-1990 (Box 52, Folder 7)
      The Orange County edition of The Christian Business and Professional Directory.
    - Biographies, Undated (Box 52, Folder 8)
      A number of documents included in the boxes of Edge City materials listing documents in each box.
    - Master List of Hanging Files, March 1992 (Box 52, Folder 9)
      A list of files in the Edge City material.
- Series 2: The Nine Nations of North America, November 1954-February 1987
  Materials pertaining to Garreau's book, "The Nine Nations of North America" published in 1989. Garreau proposed that instead of the traditional national, state and provincial borders of North America, there exist nine nations whose borders correspond to the economic and cultural similarities of their citizens. The nine nations are: New England, Quebec, The Foundry, Dixie, The Islands, The Breadbasket, Mexamerica, The Empty Quarter and Ecotopia.
  - Nine Nations, March 1979-April 1985 (Box 52, Folder 10)
    Articles, book reviews and correspondence about "The Nine Nations of North America". Also included is an early draft of part of the book; photographs and negatives of Garreau; excerpts of "Nine Nations"; and other articles dealing with the book and material in the book.
  - Miscellaneous, May 1981-February 1987 (Box 52, Folder 11)
    Articles, contact information, maps, correspondence, memos, notes, speaking contracts and book excerpts sent to Garreau after "Nine Nations" was published.
  - Redrawing the Map of the West, December 1983 (Box 52, Folder 12)
    An article and map of new borders in the western United States.
  - Les Neuf Nations De L'Amerique Du Nord, Undated (Box 52, Folder 13)
    The preface of the French language edition of "The Nine Nations of North America".
  - Business Outlook, January 1983 (Box 52, Folder 14)
    The Washington Post Business Outlook for 1983.
  - A Hierarchical Regionalization of State Economic Areas Based Upon Migration Flows, November 1976 (Box 52, Folder 15)
    "A Hierarchical Regionalization of State Economic Areas Based Upon Migration Flows" by Paul B. Slater.
  - Outlook, November 1985 (Box 52, Folder 16)
    A letter to Garreau about a contract.
  - American Seaports, Undated (Box 52, Folder 17)
    A profile of "American Seaports" a television series.
  - Les Neuf Nations, Undated (Box 52, Folder 18)
    Chapter one from the French language edition of "The Nine Nations of North America".
  - The United States of the West, March 1984 (Box 52, Folder 19)
    An article about the increasing influence of western states on politics.
  - Lede-All 1 of 5, November 1954, June 1977-September 1979 (Box 53, Folder 1)
    Articles, a Congressional Bill, book excerpts and press releases that have to do with journalism leads. Also included is a photocopy of the introduction to "Social Humanities: Toward an Integrative Discipline of Science and Values" by Raymond D. Gastil.
  - Lede-All 2 of 5, April 1977-January 1980 (Box 53, Folder 2)
    Notes, articles, maps, rough drafts, correspondence that have to do with journalism leads. Also included is a photocopy of sections of "Social Humanities: Toward an Integrative Discipline of Science and Values" by Raymond D. Gastil.
  - Lede-All 3 of 5, December 1973-April 1980 (Box 53, Folder 3)
    Articles, correspondence, maps and book excerpts about regionalism in the United States. Also included are essays and notes about taxes and urban areas.
  - Lede-All 4 of 5, November 1975-April 1980 (Box 53, Folder 4)
    Articles, notes and maps about regionalism in North America, land ownership, growth, rural and urban areas.
  - Lede-All 5 of 5, December 1978-April 1980 (Box 53, Folder 5)
    Notes, articles, book excerpts, correspondence and maps about issues raised in "The Nine Nations of North America". Also included are three Congressional documents about deteriorating infrastructure in urban and rural areas, the urban crisis, and the fiscal conditions of cities.
  - Manchester Guardian, March 1984 (Box 53, Folder 6)
    An issue of The Manchester Guardian Weekly from The Washington Post and Le Monde.
  - News clippings, September 1981-March 1984 (Box 53, Folder 7)
    Articles about regional tastes and voting.
  - National Center for Economic Alternatives, 1977 (Box 53, Folder 8)
    An essay from the National Center for Economic Alternatives about income by state.
  - Economics, April 1977-November 1985 (Box 53, Folder 9)
    Articles, notes and contact information about changing economic situations in different regions of North America.
  - Polities, November 1980 (Box 53, Folder 10)
    Information about the 1980 United States presidential election.
  - General Regionalism, August 1973-December 1982 (Box 54, Folder 1)
    Articles, magazines, press releases, reports, maps, correspondence and journals about regionalism.
  - West-Series, May 1978-June 1979 (Box 54, Folder 2)
    Articles, correspondence, notes, article drafts and maps about the western United States.
  - Water, September 1977-December 1985 (Box 54, Folder 3)
    Articles, notes, information tables, newsletters and essays about water management in the western United States. Also included is "Water For Western Energy Development Update 1977" from the Western States Water Council.
  - Energy 1 of 2, 1975-January 1980 (Box 54, Folder 4)
    Advertisements, articles, maps and data reports about oil prices and energy management and usage.
  - Energy 2 of 2, August 1978-April 1980 (Box 54, Folder 5)
    Articles, data reports, magazines, brochures and maps about energy usage in the United States.
  - Religion, June 1977-March 1980 (Box 54, Folder 6)
    Articles about religion in North America. Also included is an entry in the Historical Atlas of Religion in America about Mormons.
  - Subseries 2.1: New England, December 1971-April 1986
    Documents from Garreau's "Nine Nations" files about the "New England" section of North America. The nation includes the six states of New England, as well as the Maritime Provinces of Canada with the capital at Boston.
    - New England 1 of 4, December 1971-November 1979 (Box 55, Folder 1)
      Booklets, articles, newsletters, pamphlets, contact information and information packets about New England energy sources, farming, and culture.
    - New England 2 of 4, January 1974-November 1979 (Box 55, Folder 2)
      Articles, census reports, book excerpts, notes, about energy sources, the economy, culture and growth in New England and Atlantic Canada.
    - New England 3 of 4, February 1976-September 1982 (Box 55, Folder 3)
      Articles, notes and order forms about the economy and fuel prices in New England.
    - New England 4 of 4, August 1976-April 1980 (Box 55, Folder 4)
      Articles, booklets, notes, tourist guides and correspondence about culture, history, development, energy usage, growth, the economy and the French speaking population in New England and the Maritime Provinces of Canada. Also included is "New England: A Study in Industrial Adjustment" by R.C. Estall.
    - The Washington Post Writers Group, December 1983 (Box 55, Folder 5)
      An article from the Washington Post Writers Group about environmentalism in Rhode Island.
    - New England, May 1980-April 1986 (Box 55, Folder 6)
      Maps, event pamphlets, articles, memos, resumes, correspondence, television series proposals, advertisements and other documents about Garreau's book "The Nine Nations of North America".
    - La Nouvelle-Angleterre, Undated (Box 55, Folder 7)
      The New England chapter of the French edition of "Nine Nations".
  - Subseries 2.2: The Foundry, October 1982
    Documents from Garreau's "Nine Nations" files about "The Foundry" section of North America. The nation includes the rust belt states and provinces surrounding the four eastern Great Lakes with the capital at Detroit. It is also an area, as its name suggests that is home to industrial manufacturing and processing centers.
    - Foundry, October 1982 (Box 56, Folder 1)
      A flyer protesting the mining and processing of uranium and the October 1982 issue of "Sky", Delta airlines inflight magazine.
    - La Fonderie, Undated (Box 56, Folder 2)
      The Foundry chapter of the French edition of "Nine Nations".
  - Subseries 2.3: Aberrations, March 1974-October 1985
    Documents from Garreau's "Nine Nations" files about the "Aberrations" section of the book. Aberrations are described as "places that refuse to act in ways their locations and resources would predict." Examples include Washington, D.C., New York City, Hawaii, and Northern Alaska.
    - Washington, D.C. 1 of 2, July 1979-October 1985 (Box 56, Folder 3)
      Articles and essays about the changing demographics, sports, growth and businesses of the Washington, D.C. metropolitan area.
    - Washington, D.C. 2 of 2, June 1979-April 1983 (Box 56, Folder 4)
      Articles, notes, census reports and essays about the economy, growth, development, redevelopment, employment, culture and entertainment in the Washington, D.C. metropolitan area. Also included is a Congressional publication of a Department of the Interior and Related Agencies Appropriation Bill, 1980 and publications about attractions along the Potomac river.
    - Inuit, December 1984 (Box 56, Folder 5)
      The December 1984 issue of Inuit, the magazine of the Inuit Circumpolar Conference.
    - Inuit Arctic Policy Review, March 1984 (Box 56, Folder 6)
      The March 1984 issue of Inuit Arctic Policy Review.
    - Arctic Policy Review, January 1985 (Box 56, Folder 7)
      The January 1985 issue of Arctic Policy Review.
    - New York City 1 of 2, June 1979-September 1985 (Box 56, Folder 8)
      Articles about government, crime, transportation, education, religion, economy, housing, development, culture, tourism, energy, race and entertainment in New York City.
    - New York City 2 of 2, March 1974-December 1979 (Box 56, Folder 9)
      Articles and notes about housing, economy, tourism, music, culture, census reports, transportation, crime, immigration, preservation and government in New York City.
    - Aberrations, Undated (Box 56, Folder 10)
      The Aberrations chapter of the French edition of "Nine Nations".
    - The Arctic Policy Review, January-February 1984 (Box 56, Folder 11)
      The January-February 1984 issue of The Arctic Policy Review.
    - Inuit Arctic Policy Review, January 1984 (Box 56, Folder 12)
      The January 1984 issue of Inuit Arctic Policy Review.
    - The Arctic Policy Review, December 1983 (Box 56, Folder 13)
      The December 1983 issue of The Arctic Policy Review.
  - Subseries 2.4: Dixie, January 1985
    Documents from Garreau's "Nine Nations" files about the "Dixie" section of the book. The nation includes the states of the former Confederate States in the American southeast with the capital at Atlanta.
    - American Studies Newsletter, January 1985 (Box 57, Folder 1)
      Two copies of the January 1985 issue of American Studies Newsletter featuring articles on the American South.
    - Dixie, Undated (Box 57, Folder 2)
      The Dixie chapter of the French edition of "Nine Nations".
  - Subseries 2.5: The Islands, July 1975-October 1985
    Documents from Garreau's "Nine Nations" files about the "Islands" section of the book. The nation includes southern Florida, the Caribbean Islands, and northern Columbia and Venezuela with the capital at Miami.
    - Islands 1 of 2, July 1975-April 1980 (Box 57, Folder 3)
      Articles, essays, correspondence, notes and advertisements about the culture, history, crime, marketing, politics, economy and industry in the Caribbean. Also included is the record jacket for a Jimmy Buffet record.
    - Islands 2 of 2, December 1978-October 1985 (Box 57, Folder 4)
      Articles, pamphlets, census reports, maps, contact lists, magazines and notes about politics, culture, crime, tourism, immigration, business, finance, culture, growth, energy, real estate and weather in Latin America and the Caribbean. Also included is the 1979 Dupont Annual Report.
    - L'Archipel, Undated (Box 57, Folder 5)
      The Islands chapter from the French edition of "Nine Nations".
    - Islands 1 of 2, August 1979-January 1985 (Box 57, Folder 6)
      Articles, notes, essays maps and reports about crime, culture and travel in Latin America and the Caribbean.
    - Islands 2 of 2, May 1977-March 1980 (Box 57, Folder 7)
      Articles, notes, personal statements, pamphlets, newsletters, promotional publications, contact lists and press releases about crime, development and business in Latin America and the Caribbean. Also included is a biographical sketch of Maurice A. Ferre.
  - Subseries 2.6: MexAmerica, August 1973-January 1987
    Documents from Garreau's "Nine Nations" files about the "MexAmerica" section of the book. The nation includes southern California, Arizona, New Mexico and Texas as well as northern Mexico with the capital at Los Angeles.
    - Late Great California, December 1981-October 1984 (Box 57, Folder 8)
      Reports, articles, maps, correspondence and notes about the economy, development, commerce, politics in the American Southwest. Also included are book excerpts about the decline of the state of California.
    - MexAmerica TV Trip Notes 1 of 2, November 1985-May 1986 (Box 58, Folder 1)
      Notes, notebooks and contact information about the border area between Mexico and the United States. Also included is a map of El Paso, Texas.
    - MexAmerica TV Trip Notes 2 of 2, September 1985-June 1986 (Box 58, Folder 2)
      Notes, reports, maps, correspondence and pamphlets about finance and development in the American Southwest. Also included is an itinerary and contact list for Garreau's trip to the border area between Mexico and the United States.
    - Audiotapes Mexico, November 1985 (Box 58, Folder 3)
      Three audio tapes of notes about Mexico.
    - La MexAmerique, Undated (Box 58, Folder 4)
      The MexAmerica chapter from the French edition of "Nine Nations".
    - Mexican Recovery, October 1985 (Box 58, Folder 5)
      A Wall Street Journal article about Mexico's recovery from an earthquake.
    - Mexican Immigration in California, November 1985 (Box 58, Folder 6)
      A report and press release about current and future effects of Mexican immigration on California.
    - Mexican Population, 1975 (Box 58, Folder 7)
      Maps of the population of Mexico from 1900 to 1970.
    - Distribucion Geografica de la Poblacion en la Republica Mexicana, 1962 (Box 58, Folder 8)
      A spanish publication of population statistics for Mexico.
    - Mexico: At a Crossroads, October 1985 (Box 58, Folder 9)
      A Wall Street Journal article about Mexican politics.
    - The Border, July 1983 (Box 58, Folder 10)
      An El Paso Herald-Post special report on border relations between Mexico and the United States.
    - MexAmerica, August 1973-May 1980 (Box 58, Folder 11)
      Articles, magazines, map, department of state notes and census reports about politics, agriculture, sports, business, housing, ethnicity, border relations, growth, employment, environment, oil, development, water management, marketing and crime in the southwest United States as well as immigration, language, poverty and culture of Hispanics in the United States. Also included is "International Aspect of Development in Latin America: Geographical Perspectives".
    - Phoenix, February 1986 (Box 58, Folder 12)
      An article about the development of Phoenix, Arizona.
    - San Antonia, September 1982 (Box 58, Folder 13)
      An article about hispanic church leadership in San Antonio and a document titled "San Antonio's Place in the Technology Economy: A Review of Opportunities and a Blueprint for Action."
    - MexAmerica, Undated (Box 59, Folder 1)
      A rough draft of the MexAmerica chapter of "Nine Nations".
    - California 1 of 4, March 1978-May 1980 (Box 59, Folder 2)
      Magazines, documents, notes, articles about business, trade, industry and immigration in California.
    - California 2 of 4, September 1975-December 1979 (Box 59, Folder 3)
      Documents and articles about crime, immigration and hispanic culture in California.
    - December 1977-July 1979 (Box 59, Folder 4)
      Articles, notes and magazines about water management, transportation, employment, culture, poverty, immigration, government and crime in California and Texas. Also included is a biographical sketch of the governor of Baja California, Roberto de la Madrid Romandia, a transcript of an interview with Vilma Martinez and a publication from MALDEF.
    - California 4 of 4, May 1976-November 1979 (Box 59, Folder 5)
      Articles and documents about ethnicity, immigration, border relations and poverty in California.
    - Texas, December 1981-October 1986 (Box 59, Folder 6)
      Articles, maps, diagrams, correspondence and notes about water management, immigration, development, the economy and politics in Texas and the border area between Mexico and the United States.
    - Mex-America TV Shows, 1979-January 1987 (Box 60, Folder 1)
      Maps, notes, articles, interview transcripts, book excerpts and correspondence about immigration, oil prices, politics and finance in the border area between Mexico and the United States. Also included is notes about television productions.
    - MexAmerica 1 of 4, June 1977-March 1980 (Box 60, Folder 2)
      Articles, press releases, maps, book excerpts, notes, correspondence, sales forecasts and essays about culture, housing, business, the economy, development, language, crime, weather, poverty, politics, government, immigration, transportation and trade in border areas between Mexico and the United States.
    - MexAmerica 2 of 4, July 1978-April 1980 (Box 60, Folder 3)
      Articles, notes, maps and pamphlets about immigration, religion, water management, race, business, oil, history, development and crime in the border areas between Mexico and the United States. Also included is a calendar of events for a church.
    - MexAmerica 3 of 4, April 1978-December 1979 (Box 60, Folder 4)
      Articles, interview transcripts, notes and pamphlets about immigration, travel, religion, entertainment, resources, energy, business, ethnicity, culture and crime in the border areas between Mexico and the United States.
    - MexAmerica 4 of 4, April 1979-April 1980 (Box 60, Folder 5)
      Documents, articles, correspondence and notes about Phoenix, Arizona development, immigration, poverty, agriculture, business, water management and energy in the border areas between Mexico and the United States.
    - Mexican America, April 1980-December 1985 (Box 60, Folder 6)
      Notes, articles, magazines and reports about immigration, business, the economy, education, politics, ethnicity, development, agriculture, health care, culture about the border area between Mexico and America.
  - Subseries 2.7: Ecotopia, June 1980-September 1982
    Documents from Garreau's "Nine Nations" files about the "Ecotopia" section of the book. The nation includes the Pacific Northwest Coast from the Bay Area of California to Anchorage, Alaska with the capital at San Francisco.
    - Ecoptopia, June 1980-September 1982 (Box 61, Folder 1)
      Articles, correspondence, newsletters and notes about culture and environmentalism in the Pacific Northwest.
    - Ecotopie, Undated (Box 61, Folder 2)
      The Ecotopia chapter from the French edition of "Nine Nations".
  - Subseries 2.8: The Empty Quarter, March 1972-November 1985
    Documents from Garreau's "Nine Nations" files about "The Empty Quarter" section of the book. The nation includes the mountain states and provinces and Alaska and northern territories of Canada with a capital at Denver, Colorado.
    - Indians, March 1972-November 1985 (Box 61, Folder 3)
      Articles about Native American land development, natural resources, crimes, archaeology, politics and culture.
    - NANRDF, November 1979-April 1980 (Box 61, Folder 4)
      Documents, contact information and notes from and about the Native American Natural Resources Development Federation/
    - Indians Water Disputes, June 1978-May 1980 (Box 61, Folder 5)
      Articles and press releases about water use disputes and the relationships between Native Americans and the federal government.
    - Indian Issues Resources, June 1978-February 1980 (Box 61, Folder 6)
      Articles and notes about Native American opposition to the construction of power plants and oil drilling, as well as other conflicts between Native Americans and private organizations.
    - CERT, March 1978-February 1980 (Box 61, Folder 7)
      Articles, fact sheets, correspondence, notes and press releases about the Council of Energy Resource Tribes as well as energy production and natural resources owned by Native Americans. Also included are meeting agendas, contact information, event registration forms and book excerpts.
    - Anti-Uranium Protest, April 1980 (Box 61, Folder 8)
      An announcement of an anti-uranium protest held by the American Indian Environmental Council.
    - Newspaper Clippings, May 1978-July 1980 (Box 61, Folder 9)
      Articles about resource management and the condition of Native American communities.
    - The Western States Action, April 1980 (Box 61, Folder 10)
      A fact sheet from the American Indian Environmental Council about uranium mined on Native American land.
    - Indian, May 1978-January 1980 (Box 61, Folder 11)
      Articles about natural resources found on Native American land.